Gaines Collection of Americana
© 2006 University of Connecticut
Gaines Collection of Americana
undated, 1786-1981
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Gaines, Pierce Welsh.
6.5 linear feet
Contains individual manuscript items collected by Gaines dating from 1786-1842, including correspondence, petitions, legal documents, receipts, and reports concerning such issues as slave trade, Quakers, taxes, state of the Treasury, etc. Other materials in the collection include research notes and correspondence with fellow collectors and librarians relating to Gaines's collecting activities and historical and bibliographical publications; and inventories and notes on items in his collections.
MSS19770002
Biography
Pierce Welch Gaines was born 13 August 1905, in New Haven, Connecticut, the son of John Marshall (an efficiency expert) and Cornelia (Welch) Gaines. He attended Yale University (A.B., 1927) and Harvard University (LL.B., 1931). Gaines actively collected in the area of political Americana for the period 1789-1810. A member of the American Antiquarian Society, Bibliographical Society of University of Virginia, Connecticut Historical Society, New York Historical Society, and Acorn Club (Connecticut), Gaines resided in Fairfield, Connecticut.
An attorney by profession, Gaines worked for Allan R. Campbell (law firm, New York, N.Y., 1932-1935), U.S. Reconstruction Finance Corporation (New York, N.Y., 1935-1936), Cutis & Stoddard (law firm, Bridgeport, Conn., partner, 1936-1940), Davis Polk Wardwell Sunderland & Kiendl (New York, N.Y., attorney, 1940-1942, 1945-1946), American Telephone and Telegraph Co., (New York, N.Y., 1947-1968), U.S. Department of the Navy, Bureau of Aeronautics (Washington, D.C., assistant counsel, later counsel, 1942-1945). Mr. Gaines also served as a Trustee for the Yale Library Associates (1962-1977), Fairfield Country Day School (trustee, 1952-1963, secretary of the board, 1953-1958), Fairfield Community Chest(director, 1961-1962), and Fairfield Historical Society, (vice president, 1971-1977). Mr. Gaines died in 1977.
Published Works:
Political Works of Concealed Authorship During the Administrations of Washington, Adams and Jefferson, 1789-1809, Yale University Library, 1959.
Political Works of Concealed Authorship Relating to the United States, 1789-1810, Shoe String, 1972.
The Journal of William Stebbins (editor), Acorn Club, 1968.
William Cobbett and the United States, 1792-1835: A Bibliography with Notes and Extracts, American Antiquarian Society, 1971.
Proceedings and Yale University Library Gazette (contributor), American Antiquarian Society.
Scope and Content
The collection contains individual manuscript items collected by Mr. Gaines dating from 1786 through 1842. This portion of the collection includes correspondence, petitions, legal documents, receipts, reports concerning such issues as the slave trade, Quakers, taxes, state of the Treasury, etc. The documents were issued by the federal government (Congress) and the States (or Commonwealths of) of Vermont, Maryland, Virginia, Rhode Island, Pennsylvania, New York, and Georgia. Other materials in the collection include manuscripts of his historical and bibliographical publications, correspondence with fellow collectors and librarians concerning his collecting activities and inventories and notes on items in his collections. The book and pamphlet collections have been removed and catalogued individually.
Gaines's accession materials (3 notebooks) for the collection have been separated out and are located in the volunteer cataloger's office.
Arrangement
Correspondence has been arranged alphabetically by signatory and documents chronologically. The remainder of the collection has been sorted into six topical series. Pamphlet and book collections have been cataloged separately and are accessible via the Library's online catalogue.
Series I: Americana Collection ( undated, 1786-1842 )
Series II: Subject Files ( undated, 1949-1968 )
Series III: Correspondence ( undated,1956-1981 )
Series IV: Writings ( undated, 1792-1977 )
Series V: Materials removed from Book and Pamphlet collection ( undated )
Series VI: Catalogues, Brochures, and other Publications ( undated, 1840-1976 )
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to rare and unique books and publications. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Separated Material
The Books and Pamphlet portions of the collection have been separated from the collection and cataloged.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Persons:
Gaines, Pierce Welsh.; Washington, George, 1732-1799.; Jefferson, Thomas, 1743-1826.
Subjects:
United States. President (1789-1797: Washington).; United States. President (1801-1809: Jefferson).; Book collecting United States.; American literature--1783-1850--Bibliography.; Collectors and collecting--United States.; United States--History--Constitutional period, 1789-1809--Bibliography.; United States--Politics and government--1789-1809.; United States--History--Constitutional period, 1789-1809.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Financial records.; Manuscripts.; Galley proofs.; Administrative records.; Petitions.; Personal papers.; Inventories.
Restrictions on Access
There are no access restrictions on this collection.
Acquisition Information
The materials were received through gift and purchase from Mr. Gaines in 1977.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Americana Collection, undated, 1786-1842
  - Subseries A: Individuals, undated, 1786-1842
    - Ames, Fisher (receipt), 1792 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
    - Barry, John, 1798 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
    - Bee, Thomas, 1798 (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - Bradford, William, undated (Box 1:, Folder 4)
    - Cady, Noah (commission), undated (Box 2:, Folder 5)
    - Clinton, DeWitt, 1805 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - Dallas, Alexander J., 1786 (Box 1:, Folder 206)
    - Everett, Edward (passport), 1842 (Box 1:, Folder 207)
    - Findlay, James, 1802 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
    - Gadsden, Christopher, 1790 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
    - Gallatin, Albert (Treasury circular), 1809 (Box 2:, Folder 9)
    - Gore, C., 1806 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
    - Granger, William, 1803 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
    - Gregg, Andrew, 1803 (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - Griswold, R [oger?], 1808 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
    - Hale, Bolling, 1801 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - Hamilton, Alexander, 1790 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - Huntington, Samuel, 1800 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
    - Ingersoll, J., 1796 (Box 1:, Folder 17)
    - Izard, Ralph, 1793 (Box 1:, Folder 18)
    - Izard, Ra [lph], 1793 (Box 2:, Folder 215)
    - Lloyd, James, 1803 (Box 1:, Folder 19)
    - Lyon, James, 1798 (Box 1:, Folder 20)
    - Jefferson, Thomas, 1788 (Box 1:, Folder 21)
    - Jefferson, Thomas, 1793 (Box 1:, Folder 22)
    - Jefferson, Thomas (Pardon), 1801 (Box 2:, Folder 216)
    - Jefferson, Thomas (Speech), 1801 (Box OS:, Folder 213)
    - Jefferson, Thomas, 1808 (Box 1:, Folder 23)
    - Jefferson, Thomas, 1808 (Box 2:, Folder 24)
    - Marsh, Truman, 1796 (Box 1:, Folder 25)
    - Mitchell, Samuel L., 1803 (Box 1:, Folder 26)
    - Mitchell, Samuel L., 1807 (Box 1:, Folder 27)
    - Morris, Robert (promissory note), 1795 (Box 1:, Folder 28)
    - Morris, Robert (protest promissory note), 1798 (Box 2:, Folder 29)
    - Pickering, Thomas, 1808 (Box OS:, Folder 210)
    - Pierce, John, 1806 (Box 1:, Folder 30)
    - Townsend, David, 1812 (Box 2:, Folder 31)
    - Trumbull, Jonathan, 1804 (Box 1:, Folder 32)
    - Williams, William, 1799 (Box 1:, Folder 33)
    - Wooden, Benjamin (commission), 1805 (Box 2:, Folder 34)
  - Subseries B: Unknown location, 1794, 1808
    - Ordinance for the Suppression of Nuisances..., 1794 (Box OS:, Folder 214)
    - Complete Vindication of Mr. Ross's Character, 1808 (Box OS:, Folder 208)
  - Subseries C: United States, 1789-1809
    - Act for the Government and Regulation of Seamen in the Merchant's Service, 1790 (Box OS:, Folder 209)
    - U.S. Congress, 1791-1794 (Box 2:, Folder 37)
    - Message from Speaker of the House of Representatives, 1795 (Box 1:, Folder 39)
    - Act repealing...[Spirits distillation law], 1797 (Box 1:, Folder 41)
    - Bridge over the Potomac, 1806 (Box 2:, Folder 48)
  - Subseries D: States, undated, 1788-1808
    - Connecticut
      - Interest payment notes, 1789-1790 (Box 1:, Folder 36)
      - Tax Notice, 1800 (Box 1:, Folder 44)
    - Louisiana
      - LA. Defense of Orleans, 1806 (Box 1:, Folder 49)
    - Massachusetts, 180
      - Death of George Washington, undated (Box 1:, Folder 35)
      - Commonwealth of Massachusetts, 1792 (Box 2:, Folder 38)
      - Report of the Committee of the Senate...(2), 1806 (Box OS:, Folder 211)
    - New York, 180
      - Indenture, 1788 (Box OS:, Folder 218)
      - Court document, 1800 (Box 2:, Folder 43)
      - Cargo Insurance St. Croix to New York, 1803 (Box 2:, Folder 46)
      - Importation receipt, 1803 (Box 1:, Folder 47)
    - Pennsylvania
      - Land Deed, Lycoming County, 1794 (Box OS:, Folder 212)
      - Indenture, 1796 (Box OS:, Folder 217)
      - Plan for the establishment..., 1797 (Box 2:, Folder 40)
      - Distillery inspection (blank), 18?? (Box 1:, Folder 42)
    - Rhode Island
      - Port of Newport receipt, 1801 (Box 1:, Folder 45)
    - Virginia
      - Photocopies of materials in the Public Record Office, undated (Box OS)
- Series II: Subject Files, undated, 1949-1968
  - Appraisal Inventory, 1949 (Box 3:, Folder 50)
  - Appraisal Inventory, 1968 (Box 3:, Folder 51)
  - Book sellers, undated (Box 3:, Folder 52)
  - Collection Interests and wants, undated (Box 3:, Folder 53)
  - Gordon Harris Montague, undated (Box 3:, Folder 54)
  - References and Notes on Collections, undated (Box 6-7)
- Series III: Correspondence, undated, 1956-1981
  - Acorn Club, 1960-1972 (Box 3:, Folder 55)
  - Adams, Thomas P., 1963-1972 (Box 3:, Folder 56)
  - American Antiquarian Society, 1958-1974 (Box 3:, Folder 57)
  - Berkeley, Edmund, 1963-1974 (Box 3:, Folder 58)
  - Boyd, Julian P., 1962-1976 (Box 3:, Folder 59)
  - British Museum, 1969 (Box 3:, Folder 60)
  - Butterfield, L.H., 1963-1972 (Box 3:, Folder 61)
  - Childs, James Bennett, 1970 (Box 3:, Folder 62)
  - Connecticut Historical Society, 1956-1975 (Box 3:, Folder 63)
  - Davis, Richard Beale, 1963-1967 (Box 3:, Folder 64)
  - Fairfield Historical Society, 1971-1976 (Box 3:, Folder 65)
  - Library Committee, 1975-1976 (Box 3:, Folder 66)
  - Insurance, 1971-1973 (Box 3:, Folder 67)
  - Farnham, Thomas J., 1972 (Box 3:, Folder 68)
  - Gravell, Thomas L., 1973 (Box 3:, Folder 69)
  - Hill School, 1961 (Box 3:, Folder 70)
  - Johnson, Herbert A., 1975 (Box 3:, Folder 71)
  - Lewis Walpole Library, 1975 (Box 3:, Folder 72)
  - Library of Congress, 1965-1976 (Box 3:, Folder 73)
  - Malone, Dumas, 1970 (Box 3:, Folder 74)
  - Mount Pleasant Bookbinders, 1975-1976 (Box 3:, Folder 75)
  - National Archives, 1959 (Box 3:, Folder 76)
  - Nesheim, Kenneth, 1972-1975 (Box 3:, Folder 77)
  - Pequot-Yale deposit, 1969-1973 (Box 3:, Folder 78)
  - Pond, Walter, 1971 (Box 3:, Folder 79)
  - Robinson, Cedric L., 1972 (Box 3:, Folder 80)
  - Runge, William H., 1963-1965 (Box 3:, Folder 81)
  - Seven Gables Bookshop, undated (Box 3:, Folder 82)
  - Southbury Property, 1972 (Box 3:, Folder 83)
  - Spater, George, 1971-1981 (Box 3:, Folder 84)
  - Syrett, Harold C., 1962-1973 (Box 3:, Folder 85)
  - Talas, 1974-1975 (Box 3:, Folder 86)
  - Wells College, 1963-1971 (Box 3:, Folder 87)
  - Wetlands Regulations, 1974-1975 (Box 3:, Folder 88)
  - Wolf, Edwin, 1961-1973 (Box 3:, Folder 89)
  - Yale University Library, 1971-1972 (Box 3:, Folder 90)
- Series IV: Writings, undated, 1792-1977
  - Unidentified Notes, undated (Box 3:, Folder 91)
  - Connecticut Libel Cases, 1806-1808, undated (Box 3:, Folder 92)
  - Copyrights, undated, 1966 (Box 3:, Folder 93)
  - Journal of William Stebbins
    - Correspondence, 1965-1968 (Box 3:, Folder 94)
    - Journal of Travels to Washington City and Back (TS), undated (Box 3:, Folder 95)
    - Proofs, 1968 (Box 3:, Folder 96)
    - New Orleans Battiere, undated (Box 3:, Folder 97)
  - Political Works of Concealed Authorship, 1966-1967 (Box 3:, Folder 98)
    - Additions and Amendments, undated (Box 3:, Folder 99)
    - Correspondence, 1959-1977 (Box 3:, Folder 100)
  - Political Writings in the Young Republic, 1967 (Box 3:, Folder 101)
  - Proceedings (AAS), 1968-1976 (Box 3:, Folder 102)
  - Research Notes, undated (Box 3:, Folder 103)
  - Rider, undated (Box 3:, Folder 104)
  - William Cobbett's Account Book 1, undated (Box 3:, Folder 105)
  - William Cobbett's Account Book 2, undated (Box 4:, Folder 106)
  - William Cobbett's Account Book Galley proof, undated (Box 4:, Folder 107)
  - William Cobbett Bibliography
    - Correspondence, 1965-1976 (Box 4:, Folder 108)
    - Drafts, undated (Box 4:, Folder 109)
    - Notes, undated (Box 4:, Folder 110-116)
    - Typescript, undated (Box 4:, Folder 117)
    - Preface, undated (Box 4:, Folder 118)
    - TS copy, undated (Box 4:, Folder 119-121)
    - [17?]93-96, 1970 (Box 4:, Folder 122)
    - [17?]97-[18?]00, 1970 (Box 4:, Folder 123)
    - [18?]01-07, 1970 (Box 4:, Folder 124)
    - Final Page Proofs, 1971 (Box 4:, Folder 125)
    - Cobbett Imprints, undated (Box 4:, Folder 126)
    - Secondary Bibliography, undated (Box 4:, Folder 127)
    - Corrected Proofs, undated (Box 4:, Folder 128)
    - Letter to William Pitt transcript, 1792 (Box 4:, Folder 129)
    - Letter to Rachel Smither transcript, 1794 (Box 4:, Folder 130)
    - Letter to William Gifford transcript, 1799 (Box 4:, Folder 131)
    - Letter to John Wright transcript, 1800 (Box 4:, Folder 132)
    - Letter to John Wright transcript, 1800 (Box 4:, Folder 133)
    - Letter to John Wright transcript, 1800 (Box 4:, Folder 134)
    - Letter to William Windham transcript, 1800 (Box 4:, Folder 135)
    - Letter to Rachel Smither transcript, 1800 (Box 4:, Folder 136)
    - Short Title List, 1969 (Box 4:, Folder 137)
    - Corrected Proofs, 1971 (Box 4:, Folder 138)
- Series V: Materials removed from Book and Pamphlet collection, undated
  - Gaines 581 (Box 4:, Folder 139)
  - Gaines 582 (Box 4:, Folder 140)
  - Gaines 586 (Box 4:, Folder 141)
  - Gaines 598 (Box 4:, Folder 142)
  - Gaines 601 (Box 4:, Folder 143)
  - Gaines 607 (Box 4:, Folder 144)
  - Gaines 628 (Box 4:, Folder 145)
  - Gaines 634 (Box 4:, Folder 146)
  - Gaines 637 (Box 4:, Folder 147)
- Series VI: Catalogues, Brochures, and other Publications, undated, 1840-1976
  - 195 Magazine, 1957 (Box 5:, Folder 148)
  - American Antiquarian Society (Box 5:, Folder 149)
  - "American Sheet Music Illustration", 1973 (Box 5:, Folder 150)
  - Americanist, undated (Box 5:, Folder 151)
  - Argosy Bookstores, undated (Box 5:, Folder 152)
  - Books and Manuscripts from the Collection..., undated (Box 5:, Folder 153)
  - Boyd, Julian P., Articles of Confederation..., 1960 (Box 5:, Folder 154)
  - Brown Alumni Monthly, 1968 (Box 5:, Folder 155)
  - Bulletin of the New York Public Library, 1960-1963 (Box 5:, Folder 156)
  - Catalogue of an Exhibition of Historical..., 1959 (Box 5:, Folder 157)
  - Clark, G. Kitson, Guide for Research Students..., 1965 (Box 5:, Folder 158)
  - Collecting for Scholarship, 1959 (Box 5:, Folder 159)
  - Connecticut Historical Society Bulletin, 1970 (Box 5:, Folder 160)
  - Currey Rare Books, 1976 (Box 5:, Folder 161)
  - >Dauber & Pine Bookshops, undated (Box 5:, Folder 162)
  - Emissary and Entrepôts, 1971 (Box 5:, Folder 163)
  - Exhibition Celebrating the 75th Anniversary..., 1959 (Box 5:, Folder 164)
  - Farnham Museum Society Newsletter, 1972 (Box 5:, Folder 165)
  - Michael Ginsberg Books, undated (Box 5:, Folder 166)
  - Greenwood, F.W.P., Sermon on the death..., 1840 (Box 5:, Folder 167)
  - Grolier Club Invitations, undated (Box 5:, Folder 168)
  - Grolier Club Transactions, 1885 (Box 5:, Folder 169)
  - Lathrop C. Harper, Americana Catalogue, 1962 (Box 5:, Folder 170)
  - Headlines in History, 1976 (Box 5:, Folder 171)
  - History Today, 1972, 1973 (Box 5:, Folder 172)
  - Ivins, William, Artistic Aspects of 15th century..., 1932 (Box 5:, Folder 173)
  - Jenkins Company, American Celebration, 1976 (Box 5:, Folder 174)
  - John Hancock Insurance Co. Publications, undated (Box 5:, Folder 175)
  - Bernhard Knollenberg, 1973 (Box 5:, Folder 176)
  - Lawrence Counselman Wroth, 1971 (Box 5:, Folder 177)
  - George S. MacManus Company, undated (Box 5:, Folder 178)
  - Massachusetts Historical Society, 1971 (Box 5:, Folder 179)
  - Midland Notes #85, 87, undated (Box 5:, Folder 180)
  - Mirror of the Indian, 1958 (Box 5:, Folder 181)
  - New Books from Virginia, 1974 (Box 5:, Folder 182)
  - New York Herald Tribune, 1958 (Box 5:, Folder 183)
  - Nineteenth Century Fiction, undated (Box 5:, Folder 184)
  - David L. O'Neal Booksellers, 1976 (Box 5:, Folder 185)
  - Old South leaflets, undated (Box 5:, Folder 186)
  - Ordeal of Henry Bird, undated (Box 5:, Folder 187)
  - Origin of the Serif, undated (Box 5:, Folder 188)
  - Our American Government, 1953 (Box 5:, Folder 189)
  - Papers of the Bibliographic Society of America, 1963 (Box 5:, Folder 190)
  - Parke-Bernet Galleries, 1966 (Box 5:, Folder 191)
  - Bernard Quaritch's Catalogue, undated (Box 5:, Folder 192)
  - Reprint Company Publishers, undated (Box 5:, Folder 193)
  - Society of the Cincinnati in the State of CT, 1958-1959 (Box 5:, Folder 194)
  - Steele, Richard C., Isiah Thomas, 1975 (Box 5:, Folder 195)
  - Henry Stevens son & Stiles, undated (Box 5:, Folder 196)
  - Stevenson, Allan, Observations on Paper..., 1961 (Box 5:, Folder 197)
  - Swann Galleries, undated (Box 5:, Folder 198)
  - University of Virginia and Virginia brochures, undated (Box 5:, Folder 199)
  - Wells College Bulletin, undated (Box 5:, Folder 200)
  - Wesleyan Library Notes, 1969 (Box 5:, Folder 201)
  - Ximenes Rare Books, undated (Box 5:, Folder 202)
  - Yale University Press, undated (Box 5:, Folder 203)
  - Yale University Library Gazette, 1955-1972 (Box 5:, Folder 204)
  - Zeitler and Ver Brugge Booksellers, 1976 (Box 5:, Folder 205)